<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Web on Maxime Moreillon</title>
    <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/web/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Web on Maxime Moreillon</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/web/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Neighbridge homepage</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/e6687cab-6c3d-41bc-b713-7ea50b6e6cb6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/e6687cab-6c3d-41bc-b713-7ea50b6e6cb6/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Neighbridge is an international community in Nagoya. I&amp;rsquo;ve been joining their events for quite some time and heard that their organizers wanted to improve their online visibility. As this relates to my line of work, I provided some help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started by designing a simple web page in pure HTML and CSS. Here, the objective was to use simple tools so that the organizers could later edit the code themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wardrobe and outfits management web app</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/0c1a7a47-c651-472d-a867-e1e2b040e997/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/0c1a7a47-c651-472d-a867-e1e2b040e997/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever bought a piece of clothing only to come home and realize you already had a similar one in your wardrobe? This web application aims at solving this problem by allowing users to register their garments in a database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/61f2b47035a52f9bb09e4eef&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the application provides a way to register complete outfits and list the various garments that are parts it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/62b8fa733bbcba1c3e77be8c&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application consists of a Node.js back-end which stores garment information in a MongoDB database. It also provides a REST API built using Express to exchange data with the application&amp;rsquo;s GUI. The latter is a Vue.js single page application featuring UI components from the Vuetify library.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TDD for an Express application</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/463/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/463/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TDD has been proven to significantly reduce the amount of bugs in software releases. Moreover, with CI/CD systems, tests can be run automatically before the application deployment, preventing a faulty application to reach its end user. This guide goes through the steps required to set up a TDD workflow with an Express application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-example-application&#34;&gt;An example application&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the application we would like to test. Here we&amp;rsquo;ll use the following Express application:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>File POSTer</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/441/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/441/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many web applications rely on the upload of files from client to server via a POST request. The content-type of this request is generally multipart/form-data. When developing the server-side of such application, being able to quickly test the upload feature can greatly increase productivity. So, I designed this simple web application that can POST a file to any URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/61a2ddd34b39954ad9dae5c4&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application is built using Vue.js with the Vuetify plugin and uses Axios to send the HTTP requests. Its source code is available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.com/moreillon_k8s_home/file-poster&#34;&gt;GitLab&lt;/a&gt;. The application can be deployed as a Docker container, for which the image is available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://hub.docker.com/repository/docker/moreillon/file-poster&#34;&gt;Docker Hub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling profile webpage</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/339/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/339/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Foreign models are quite in demand in Japan and as such it is not uncommon for foreigners living there to have a side activity in the modeling industry. I had the chance to meet the manager a &lt;a href=&#34;https://azs-group.jp/&#34;&gt;AZS entertainment&lt;/a&gt; and was told that the agency was currently recruiting. So, since I am always looking for new life experiences, I decided to join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AZS entertainment was kind enough to prepare a &lt;a href=&#34;https://azs-group.jp/manage_post/990&#34;&gt;webpage for my profile on their website&lt;/a&gt;. However, since I own the maximemoreillon.com domain, I decided that I could also host my own profile web page here. Thus, I made a simple page with some of my pictures, body measurements and links, deployed at &lt;a href=&#34;http://modeling.maximemoreillon.com&#34;&gt;modeling.maximemoreillon.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Food manager</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/573/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/573/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The other day, I found myself putting on some weight. This rather surprised me as I thought I was having a healthy diet and exercised almost daily. To identify the root of the problem, I decided to start measuring my calorie intake as well as the macronutrients that constitute said intake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve this, I built a simple web application using the MEVN stack. The application serves two purposes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Store information about the various food I eat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the total calorie count and macronutrients constitution of a given list of food&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;food-database&#34;&gt;Food database&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to compute a calorie count or macronutrient constitution of a meal, one must first know those values for each individual piece of food in it. This information is stored in a MongoDB collection, managed by its own model, controllers, routes and view.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MQTT control dashboard</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/555/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/555/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the cloud native multi-user MQTT platform deployed, I started designing IoT devices that I could distribute to end users. However, without a GUI, interacting with those devices would be difficult. Of course, one could install applications like MQTT dash or similar but this would require tedious configuration such as MQTT broker and topics. I wanted to give users a simpler UX so I made this simple control interface that automatically displays a users devices and allows those to be controlled.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A template for Vue.js applications</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/28/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I have built multiple Vue.js applications. Although their business logic differs, those applications often share similar components such as a navigation panel, a header with my logo and an authentication mechanism. Writing those from scratch for each application would be time consuming so I designed an application template that can be installed using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.npmjs.com/package/@moreillon/vue_application_template&#34;&gt;NPM&lt;/a&gt; to bootstrap my projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/615255af9a075f4e3559ce34&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The template integrates in existing Vue.js applications as a component. By default, it wraps the router-view component and adds the following UI components to the app:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>API tester</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/518/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/518/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are multiple tools available for API testing, Postman and Insomnia being probably the most popular. However, those are desktop applications that need to be installed. I wanted a solution that I can use in the browser so I made a simple web application to achieve basic API testing functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This application can send GET, POST, DELETE, PUT and PATCH HPP requests and allows the user to add headers or a JSON body to the request.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Group and User Pickers</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/134/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/134/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;a href=&#34;https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/585&#34;&gt;user management&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/398&#34;&gt;group management microservices&lt;/a&gt;, users and their groups can be easily queried through HTTP requests. However, the GUI that the user interacts with must also be properly designed so as to provide an optimal UX. To facilitate the query of users via the GUI, I designed a group and user picker component for Vue.js that can be easily installed using NPM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;group-picker&#34;&gt;Group picker&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the group management microservice, users are divided into groups. So, I first designed a group picker that allows to query the node corresponding to a specific group in the database. This picker takes advantage of the tree structure of groups to show those in orderly fashion. The component has been made so as to emit the group properties when a selection is made.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User management microservice based on Neo4J</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/585/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/585/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Web applications commonly require a user database and the management logic for it. Having to build such software infrastructure for each individual app would be time consuming so I designed a general-purpose user management microservice that can be easily integrated in a project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, the service consists of a Node.js + Express API which stores and manages users as nodes in a Neo4J database. here, Neo4J was chosen so that other apps could add their own nodes to it and thus benefit from the advantages of a graph database.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Camera viewer</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/519/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/519/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;IP cameras are cheaper than ever and with the ESP32-CAM boards it is now possible to stream video for less than USD 10. However, IP cameras are commonly either only accessible from within their network, or use servers from third party companies to allow users to see the video feed from anywhere in the world. As both scenarios are inconvenient, I decided to create a camera viewer application that can proxy the video feed to a web interface.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Group management microservice</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/398/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/398/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a graph database Neo4j is a great choice to manage highly relational data. On the other side, a great number of applications feature at least some form of user management system. With Neo4j, those users can be store as nodes and connected to other items via relationships. A typical example would be a blog, where both articles and users are individual nodes while authorships are represented by a relationship.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RESTful API design</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/15/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are four main kind of operations when working with a database: &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt;reate, &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;ead, &lt;strong&gt;U&lt;/strong&gt;pdate and &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;elete (CRUD). However, databases are usually not exposed directly to the clients. Instead, those operations are performed by a server side application with a client-facing API. The most common type of APIs nowadays are based on HTTP. An HTTP API can be built with complete freedom. However, guidelines for best-practice HTTP API design have been created. An API following those guidlines is called a REST (or RESTful) API.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>APIs: Why and how</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/33/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From a simplistic point of view, software can be seen as a combination of operations performed on data. Data comes in, gets processed through a series of functions and some result comes out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/image?id=5ec5d30a55b0c12424749cf4&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;As an example, here is a simple function that computes the area of a circle from its radius as it would be written in JavaScript:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;function area_of_circle(radius){
  return Math.PI * radius * radius
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;With this implementation, this function can be used within other parts of the code. For instance, one could later use it to compute the volume of a cylinder as so:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fixed asset management system</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/87/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/87/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many companies rely on spreadsheets to keep track of their fixed assets. However, spreadsheets are commonly designed to be edited manually, which makes automation difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application presented in this article is a fixed asset management system based on a MongoDB database, and provides a REST API which makes it possible for other applications or devices to perform CRUD operations on the data, hence greatly improving the automation potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application uses the MEVN ( MongoDB, Express, Vue.js, Node.js ) stack and thus offers a browser-based GUI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Image upload microservice</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/43/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/43/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An image is worth a thousand words and probably even more if comparing their size in bytes. When designing my CMS, I originally intended to store images directly in the article, encoded in Base64. However, this would considerably increase the size of each article, making the whole CMS slow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally images would be loaded independently from articles, which requires them to be served separately. Consequently, I created a simple image management microservice that allows to upload images through a web interface and serves them wherever required.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Force IE to use its latest version</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/200/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/200/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Depending on the settings, Internet Explorer can decide to render webpages using a lower version, which can result in compatibility issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To force IE to use its latest, the following can be added to an HTML document&amp;rsquo;s head:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;meta http-equiv=&amp;#34;X-UA-Compatible&amp;#34; content=&amp;#34;IE=edge&amp;#34; /&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSS basics</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/231/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/231/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;HTML defines the content of a web page but not its aesthetics. Styling a document is achieved using CSS, which stands for Cascading Style Sheet and is another language that web browsers can interpret.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;inline-css&#34;&gt;Inline CSS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest way to style elements of an HTML document is to add the &amp;ldquo;style&amp;rdquo; property in the HTML tag. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;p style=&amp;#39;color:blue;&amp;#39;&amp;gt;This is a paragraph and it is blue&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;property:value&lt;/strong&gt; is the CSS semantics used to style elements and every statement should be terminated by a semicolon (;). As such, multiple properties can be styled:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finances management web app</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/165/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/165/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most banks nowadays provide e-banking interfaces that allow clients to monitor the state of their accounts. However, each bank has its own system and the provided interfaces sometimes lack functionalities. Consequently, I decided to create my own finance dashboard, that combines information regarding multiple accounts. Currently I use it to keep track of my bank accounts balance over time as well as provide a breakdown of my transactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/60b1cf1043b282317cabca3b&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The back-end of the application is built using NodeJS while data is stored in a MongoDB collection for transactions and InfluxDB for the balance history. On the other hand, the front end is built using VueJS and uses ChartsJS for plots.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HTML basics</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/176/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/176/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;HTML stands for HyperText Markup Language. It is used to describe the content of a webpage to web browsers. Originally, web browsers were designed to display text documents and so HTML was used to define the various parts making up those documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tags&#34;&gt;Tags&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTML uses tags to define the attributes of content such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;This is a pararaph&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this example, the text &amp;ldquo;This is a paragraph&amp;rdquo; is defined as a paragraph because it is surrounded by &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tags. Note the &amp;ldquo;/&amp;rdquo; for the tag after the content, which implies that it is a closing tag.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This very application, a CMS based on Neo4J</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/112/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/112/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Publishing articles on a website can be as simple as uploading HTML files to a web server. However, writing articles in raw HTML can be time consuming. A content management system (CMS) is an application designed to solve this issue by providing a simple way to create and manage web content directly from the web browser. There are many CMSs available, namely Wordpress or Joomla but I decided to create my own as a form of practice and in order to have it highly customized to my needs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
