<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Express on Maxime Moreillon</title>
    <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/express/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Express on Maxime Moreillon</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/express/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Auto CRUD</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/1d5d4606-7732-40ec-b7b0-24afdf8b7d85/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/1d5d4606-7732-40ec-b7b0-24afdf8b7d85/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most web applications that manage data in a database perform at least some form of create, read, update or delete (CRUD) operations on stored records. Moreover, web applications also often expose those operations via a REST API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most database tables - corresponding to the entities manged by the application - need their own CRUD controller and set of HTTP endpoints. Because of this, large applications can quickly become tedious to develop and maintain. However, the logic for each table is usually quite similar.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web based approval system</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/627bd1d8-79e3-4b3b-8c71-95e76c937d93/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/627bd1d8-79e3-4b3b-8c71-95e76c937d93/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the COVID-19 and the introduction of remote work, a many japanese companies were struggling with the approval of documents, since those needed to be physically stamped with one&amp;rsquo;s personal seal named Hanko.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to solve this issue by creating a web application to keep track of approvals (or rejections). The application, allows users to submit application forms of various kinds to recipients of their choice. Each recipient can decide wether to approve or reject the submission.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MQTT Logger</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/5aa92bbf-956c-43a9-8f3c-e0bdacd6412d/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/5aa92bbf-956c-43a9-8f3c-e0bdacd6412d/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve used various IoT sensors which collect data that is then broadcast using MQTT. Those sensors generally broadcast individual measurements without saving any form of history locally. Consequently, if one would want to plot time-series graphs, the data would first need to be stored somewhere. This is the objective of the application presented in this article, named MQTT Logger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MQTT Logger is a Node.js application which subscribes to MQTT topics of IoT sensors and stores the data that those published in an InfluxDB time-series database.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weight tracker</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/4d7c6224-9574-4015-b45b-c6f2cbfb4e4c/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/4d7c6224-9574-4015-b45b-c6f2cbfb4e4c/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Managing one&amp;rsquo;s body weight can be quite a challenge. And as the quote from Peter Drucker goes, &amp;ldquo;You can&amp;rsquo;t manage what you can&amp;rsquo;t measure&amp;rdquo;. So, I built a body weight scale that can upload data to an API of my choice, which was the object of &lt;a href=&#34;https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/160&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;a href=&#34;https://thingspeak.com/&#34;&gt;ThingSpeak&lt;/a&gt; to store this data for some time but then decided I wanted to have my own storing system. Thus I designed a simple Node.js application to handle this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wardrobe and outfits management web app</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/0c1a7a47-c651-472d-a867-e1e2b040e997/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/0c1a7a47-c651-472d-a867-e1e2b040e997/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever bought a piece of clothing only to come home and realize you already had a similar one in your wardrobe? This web application aims at solving this problem by allowing users to register their garments in a database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/61f2b47035a52f9bb09e4eef&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the application provides a way to register complete outfits and list the various garments that are parts it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/62b8fa733bbcba1c3e77be8c&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application consists of a Node.js back-end which stores garment information in a MongoDB database. It also provides a REST API built using Express to exchange data with the application&amp;rsquo;s GUI. The latter is a Vue.js single page application featuring UI components from the Vuetify library.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Express authorization middleware</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/247/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/247/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many applications require some form of authorization mechanism to prevent users from accessing restricted content. Authenticated users are commonly in possession of a cookie containing identification data. With the authentication microservice that I designed, this cookie contains a JWT that contains the user&amp;rsquo;s username. This JWT is sent in the authorization header of HTTP requests. Thus, authorization can be performed easily within each application by simply decoding the JWT. To do so, I designed this simple middleware for ExpressJS.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LINE Bot</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/86/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/86/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;LINE, the most popular messaging app in Japan, provides an API to build bots. Those bots can react to receive messages or send their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to use this API to build a simple notification microservice. Whenever a message is posted on its /notify endpoint, the message gets sent to my smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In previous versions of the service, I also experimented with the processing of messages sent to the service. For instance, checking my apartment&amp;rsquo;s electricity consumption.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finances management web app</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/165/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/165/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most banks nowadays provide e-banking interfaces that allow clients to monitor the state of their accounts. However, each bank has its own system and the provided interfaces sometimes lack functionalities. Consequently, I decided to create my own finance dashboard, that combines information regarding multiple accounts. Currently I use it to keep track of my bank accounts balance over time as well as provide a breakdown of my transactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/60b1cf1043b282317cabca3b&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The back-end of the application is built using NodeJS while data is stored in a MongoDB collection for transactions and InfluxDB for the balance history. On the other hand, the front end is built using VueJS and uses ChartsJS for plots.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solar power setup</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/186/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/186/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got my hands on a 600W 12V inverter so I decided to experiment with generating my own electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inverter converts 12V DC power into 100V AC electricity which can be used for household appliances. Here, the 12V DC power is supplied by a 45Ah lead-acid battery, which would allow the inverter to run at full power for slightly short of an hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/62b91cd73bbcbae9ee77c094&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The battery is charged by a 30W solar panel, through a 10A solar charge controller. Thus, with full sunlight, the battery would theoretically be charged in about 18 hours. I don&amp;rsquo;t intend to use the inverter on a daily basis so the slow rate of charge isn&amp;rsquo;t so much of a limitation. If needed, I could still add another solar panel in parallel in order to boost the charging current.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
