<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Helm on Maxime Moreillon</title>
    <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/helm/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Helm on Maxime Moreillon</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/helm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A GUI for ChartMuseum</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/e1d7dd0b-83b9-454e-a6e5-8e72bca46902/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/e1d7dd0b-83b9-454e-a6e5-8e72bca46902/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://chartmuseum.com/&#34;&gt;ChartMuseum&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source Helm chart repository server which can be used as a self-hosted alternative to &lt;a href=&#34;https://artifacthub.io/&#34;&gt;Artifact Hub&lt;/a&gt;. Although it originally consists of only a server-side application to be interacted with via a REST API, its official UI, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chartmuseum/ui&#34;&gt;ChartMuseumUI&lt;/a&gt;, can be deployed to interact with ChartMuseum graphically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, ChartMuseumUI seems to be broken and the GitHub repository has been inactive for years now. Thus, I decided to make my own GUI for ChartMuseum.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distributing a Helm chart on Artifact Hub</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/626/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/626/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Building applications in a microservice architecture has become more and more popular recently. With this design pattern, an application is composed of multiple services that run independently and generally share data across network protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of such application could be an e-commerce website where users, product inventory or orders are all managed by their own respective independent service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since all services are independent, deploying an application to Kubernetes involves the deployment of a large amount of resources such as deployments, services, PVCs, which can quickly become tedious if done by hand. To solve this problem, applications can be packaged using Helm, which takes care of deploying all the necessary resources. An application packaged with Helm is called a chart. Similarly to how Docker containers are spawned from container images, in helm, applications are spawned from Helm Charts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
