<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>CAD on Maxime Moreillon</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/cad/</link><description>Recent content in CAD on Maxime Moreillon</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/cad/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Rebuilding the Odroid XU4 server</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/e321210f-1643-4db8-8dae-6e2a8b71df87/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/e321210f-1643-4db8-8dae-6e2a8b71df87/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/390">In a previous article&lt;/a> I showcased a simple home server built around an Odroid XU4, which I dismantled after migrating to a full-size desktop computer. However, having the Odroid laying around unused was a bit of a waste and I recently started needing a secondary file server to store data backups. So I decided to build a new server with the single board computer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The core hardware remained similar to the original server: the Odroid itself, a hard disk connected via USB to SATA converter and a power supply. However, this time I decided to package the components in a compact PC case.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3D printed mount for USB dock</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/d3224302-ba33-437e-919c-b8c463f29eec/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/d3224302-ba33-437e-919c-b8c463f29eec/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recenly got myself an USB ype C dock for my laptop. This accessory quite convenient as it allows me to connect my laptop to power, my external monitor and USB peripherals with just one cable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/62ea71be27a6008518376123" alt="Article image">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dock itself works fine but because of the way its ports are laid out, it makes a mess of wires on my desk. To solve the issue, I decided to mount the USB dock on the back of my laptop stand.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3D printed solder spool holder</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/586/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/586/</guid><description>&lt;p>One day I got fed up with my solder spool rolling around all the time so I designed this simple spool holder in Fusion360 and 3D printed it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/614eac539a075f54f559c415" alt="">&lt;img src="https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/614eac5d9a075f3fd559c419" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The STL files for this project are available on &lt;a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:5145144">Thingiverse&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>General purpose IoT button</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/483/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/483/</guid><description>&lt;p>Over the years, I have built multiple IoT devices ranging from AC controllers to ceiling lights. Usually, I would control those devices using my smartphone or computer but sometimes a physical button can be more convenient. Thus, I designed this simple IoT button which publishes MQTT messages when pressed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/6148102f5d171a137f416ccb" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At its core, the button integrates my ESP12-F base PCB, which features a switch connected to GPIO0 used to put the ESP8266 in programming mode. After a successful boot, the GPIO0 can be used freely so I wrote a simple firmware that publishes an MQTT message when the pin gets pulled LOW.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sign holders for COVID-19 prevention</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/462/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/462/</guid><description>&lt;p>Compared to other countries, Japan did not enforce a strict lockdown on its population during the COVID-19 pandemic. As a result, most bars and restaurants continued their operations as usual. However, in order to prevent the spread of the virus as much as possible, the staff of my local pub printed out signs asking customers to not leave their table without wearing a mask.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As they didn&amp;rsquo;t have anything to hold the signs on the table, I offered to use my 3D printer to solve the problem.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3D printed bracket for fume extractor</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/522/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/522/</guid><description>&lt;p>I got myself a fume extractor but it takes a rather large amount of real-estate on my desk. I decided to mount it on an arm so that I could easily move it out of the way so I designed and 3D printed an attachment bracket for it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/614fd10f9a075f99a459c899" alt="">The bracket was designed in Fusion 360&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/614fd8ca9a075faaea59c8ad" alt="">And then printed on my QIDI Tech 1&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/614fd97c9a075f778d59c8b1" alt="">It ended up fitting the fume extractor nicely&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>IoT lock</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/237/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/237/</guid><description>&lt;p>Have you ever left your apartment and couldn&amp;rsquo;t remember if you locked your front door or not? Sadly, if it is unlocked, there is not much you can do about it until you get back home. This system is an attempt to solve the problem. Simply put, it consists of attaching an actuator to the door&amp;rsquo;s original locking mechanism and control it via WiFi.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I chose an MG996R as an actuator for its sufficient torque and angle range (180 deg). Most of the parts for this project have been 3D printed and designed in Fusion 360. The STL files are available on &lt;a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:2462482">Thingiverse&lt;/a>. The servo&amp;rsquo;s shaft and the door&amp;rsquo;s locking mechanism are connected with parts designed specially so as to have a 90 degree play between them. This allows the lock to be operated normally without having the servo interfering.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>