<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>InfluxDB on Maxime Moreillon</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/influxdb/</link><description>Recent content in InfluxDB on Maxime Moreillon</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/influxdb/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>MQTT Logger</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/5aa92bbf-956c-43a9-8f3c-e0bdacd6412d/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/5aa92bbf-956c-43a9-8f3c-e0bdacd6412d/</guid><description>&lt;p>Over the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve used various IoT sensors which collect data that is then broadcast using MQTT. Those sensors generally broadcast individual measurements without saving any form of history locally. Consequently, if one would want to plot time-series graphs, the data would first need to be stored somewhere. This is the objective of the application presented in this article, named MQTT Logger.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>MQTT Logger is a Node.js application which subscribes to MQTT topics of IoT sensors and stores the data that those published in an InfluxDB time-series database.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Weight tracker</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/4d7c6224-9574-4015-b45b-c6f2cbfb4e4c/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/4d7c6224-9574-4015-b45b-c6f2cbfb4e4c/</guid><description>&lt;p>Managing one&amp;rsquo;s body weight can be quite a challenge. And as the quote from Peter Drucker goes, &amp;ldquo;You can&amp;rsquo;t manage what you can&amp;rsquo;t measure&amp;rdquo;. So, I built a body weight scale that can upload data to an API of my choice, which was the object of &lt;a href="https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/160">this article&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I used &lt;a href="https://thingspeak.com/">ThingSpeak&lt;/a> to store this data for some time but then decided I wanted to have my own storing system. Thus I designed a simple Node.js application to handle this.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Finances management web app</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/165/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/165/</guid><description>&lt;p>Most banks nowadays provide e-banking interfaces that allow clients to monitor the state of their accounts. However, each bank has its own system and the provided interfaces sometimes lack functionalities. Consequently, I decided to create my own finance dashboard, that combines information regarding multiple accounts. Currently I use it to keep track of my bank accounts balance over time as well as provide a breakdown of my transactions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/60b1cf1043b282317cabca3b" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The back-end of the application is built using NodeJS while data is stored in a MongoDB collection for transactions and InfluxDB for the balance history. On the other hand, the front end is built using VueJS and uses ChartsJS for plots.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Solar power setup</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/186/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/186/</guid><description>&lt;p>I got my hands on a 600W 12V inverter so I decided to experiment with generating my own electricity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The inverter converts 12V DC power into 100V AC electricity which can be used for household appliances. Here, the 12V DC power is supplied by a 45Ah lead-acid battery, which would allow the inverter to run at full power for slightly short of an hour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/62b91cd73bbcbae9ee77c094" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The battery is charged by a 30W solar panel, through a 10A solar charge controller. Thus, with full sunlight, the battery would theoretically be charged in about 18 hours. I don&amp;rsquo;t intend to use the inverter on a daily basis so the slow rate of charge isn&amp;rsquo;t so much of a limitation. If needed, I could still add another solar panel in parallel in order to boost the charging current.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>IoT Current consumption monitoring system</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/83/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/83/</guid><description>&lt;p>When you don&amp;rsquo;t know how much power your air conditioner draws, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to leave it running without feeling too guilty. And then the electricity bill comes&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The objective of this project is to get an approximate measurement of how much electric power is being used in my apartment. Additionally, for the sake of safety, the measurement system should not require altering the electrical wiring currently in place. In other words, the measurement should be non-invasive.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>