<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vue.js on Maxime Moreillon</title>
    <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/vue.js/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Vue.js on Maxime Moreillon</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/vue.js/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>MQTThree</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/2e301bdf-99eb-49cc-8c11-02ac8f0a4f72/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/2e301bdf-99eb-49cc-8c11-02ac8f0a4f72/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on a few projects involving digital twins. At its core, a digital twin is simply a digital representation, oftentimes in 3D, of a physical system. Such representation commonly provides information about the system as well as ways of interactions. On the physical system, this is can be accomplished with IoT devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having to build a dedicated application for each digital twin would be tedious so I designed a simple framework to make the process more convenient. The framework uses Three.js for the 3D representation of the system and MQTT to interact with its IoT devices, which led to the name MQTThree.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vue3 Options vs Composition API</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/dab7a1ac-0d3e-4c8f-8e5c-6a724ad97b31/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/dab7a1ac-0d3e-4c8f-8e5c-6a724ad97b31/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This article presents code snippets illustrating how to transition from the Options API to the Composition API in Vue 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the options API, reactive variables are defined in data():&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;template&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;x: {{ x }}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/template&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;
export default {
  data() {
    return {
      x: 2,
    };
  },
};
&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using the composition API, reactive variables are defined as refs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;template&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;x: {{ x }}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/template&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;script setup&amp;gt;
import { ref } from &amp;#34;vue&amp;#34;;
const x = ref(2);
&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When using the options API, methods are written in the property of the same name:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rebuilding the GUI of this CMS with Nuxt 3</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/8c63c27c-e250-4207-a284-971a33096d5b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/8c63c27c-e250-4207-a284-971a33096d5b/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The GUI of this CMS has gone through multiple versions and revisions. It started as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://vuejs.org/&#34;&gt;Vue.js&lt;/a&gt; SPA but was then turned into a &lt;a href=&#34;https://nuxt.com/&#34;&gt;Nuxt&lt;/a&gt; SSR application to improve SEO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, Nuxt version 3 was released so I decided, once again, to rewrite this GUI from scratch, mainly as an excuse to learn about the newest frameworks available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside Nuxt 3, this rebuild was also an opportunity to leverage TypeScript and the Vue.js composition API.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A simple comparison of Svelte and Vue</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/f027e7b5-2aef-4ea4-8bc6-c52c50c3eaf1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/f027e7b5-2aef-4ea4-8bc6-c52c50c3eaf1/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since its introduction in 2019, Svelte has quickly become one of the most loved JavaScript framework overtaking Vue.js in the State of JS ranking 2021 survey. This article presents a simple comparison of Vue.js and Svelte as an attempt to explain why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;vuejs&#34;&gt;Vue.js&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comparison starts with the Vue.js implementation of a simple counter button. As of version 3 of Vue.js, components can be written in either the Options API of Composition API fashion so both are shown hereunder.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vue Router setup in Vue 3</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/07acf065-3dbb-4c7e-86cf-7a0769ec7379/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/07acf065-3dbb-4c7e-86cf-7a0769ec7379/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: an option to add the Vue-router has now been integrated in Vite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, when creating a Vue project using the Vue CLI, the Vue Router could be installed easily by running vue add router. However, with Vue 3 and Vite, the router is installed manually. This can be done with NPM:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm install vue-router@4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once installed, the configuration of the router can be done by creating a dedicated .js file in the src directory of the app. To mimic the structure of Vue 2 projects, the router config file is named index.js, to be created in a folder called router, sub-folder of src. A basic content would look as follows:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web based approval system</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/627bd1d8-79e3-4b3b-8c71-95e76c937d93/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/627bd1d8-79e3-4b3b-8c71-95e76c937d93/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the COVID-19 and the introduction of remote work, a many japanese companies were struggling with the approval of documents, since those needed to be physically stamped with one&amp;rsquo;s personal seal named Hanko.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to solve this issue by creating a web application to keep track of approvals (or rejections). The application, allows users to submit application forms of various kinds to recipients of their choice. Each recipient can decide wether to approve or reject the submission.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using v-model on a prop</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/76fbaccb-e02e-4b16-bcdb-f3f9e1b1cc31/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/76fbaccb-e02e-4b16-bcdb-f3f9e1b1cc31/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With Vue.js, passing data to a child component is generally achieved using props. However, mutating props from a child component is generally considered bad practice. Instead, child components must invoque the prop update from their parent using $emit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this purpose, computed values can be leveraged as they provide ways to define custom getters and setters. In this case, the get() method can simply return the value passed as prop by the parent while set() emits the desired new value.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wardrobe and outfits management web app</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/0c1a7a47-c651-472d-a867-e1e2b040e997/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/0c1a7a47-c651-472d-a867-e1e2b040e997/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever bought a piece of clothing only to come home and realize you already had a similar one in your wardrobe? This web application aims at solving this problem by allowing users to register their garments in a database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/61f2b47035a52f9bb09e4eef&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the application provides a way to register complete outfits and list the various garments that are parts it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/62b8fa733bbcba1c3e77be8c&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application consists of a Node.js back-end which stores garment information in a MongoDB database. It also provides a REST API built using Express to exchange data with the application&amp;rsquo;s GUI. The latter is a Vue.js single page application featuring UI components from the Vuetify library.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A template for Vue.js applications</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/28/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I have built multiple Vue.js applications. Although their business logic differs, those applications often share similar components such as a navigation panel, a header with my logo and an authentication mechanism. Writing those from scratch for each application would be time consuming so I designed an application template that can be installed using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.npmjs.com/package/@moreillon/vue_application_template&#34;&gt;NPM&lt;/a&gt; to bootstrap my projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/615255af9a075f4e3559ce34&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The template integrates in existing Vue.js applications as a component. By default, it wraps the router-view component and adds the following UI components to the app:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
