<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>RFID on Maxime Moreillon</title>
    <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/rfid/</link>
    <description>Recent content in RFID on Maxime Moreillon</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/rfid/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>An RFID ring as a front door key</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/523/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/523/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Global warming and the COVID-19 pandemic are some the many challenges humanity is having to face. However, I somehow decided that the problem I was going to solve is having to take my keys out of my pocket whenever I lock or unlock my front door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of a literal key, I would ideally have some form of access token that stays within hands reach and can unlock my door. In fact, I figured that it could actually be on my hand and thus went shopping for an RFID ring on AliExpress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RFID wristband</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/589/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/589/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;RFID tags are great but often easy to lose. To solve this problem, I designed this case for an RFID tag, which can be worn on one&amp;rsquo;s wrist using a standard watch strap. The case was designed using Fusion360 and then 3D printed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/614eaa369a075f73f659c403&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RFID tag is slim enough to fit in the enclosure and is secured using the provided adhesive&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/614eaa419a075f432e59c407&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The STL file for this project is available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:5145141&#34;&gt;Thingiverse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IoT RFID reader</title>
      <link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/79/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/79/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;RFID is a convenient technology for access control and authentication. In this project, I connected an RC522 RFID reader to an ESP32 in order to use it for IoT applications. Additionally, to provide feedback to the user, the ESP32 is also connected to an SSD1306 OLED display and a buzzer. I chose an ESP32 over an ESP8266 simply because of the amount of GPIOs required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/5e786e6f6f2c2a9eb519cad6&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intended to build multiple of those readers but it would take too much time to make them using protoboard. So, I designed a custom PCB using &lt;a href=&#34;https://easyeda.com/&#34;&gt;EasyEDA&lt;/a&gt; and had multiple copies manufactured by &lt;a href=&#34;https://jlcpcb.com/&#34;&gt;JLCPCB&lt;/a&gt;. A link to the complete EasyEDA project can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://easyeda.com/m.moreillon/iot_rfid_reader&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
