<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Svelte on Maxime Moreillon</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/svelte/</link><description>Recent content in Svelte on Maxime Moreillon</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/tags/svelte/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Countries tracker</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/bd9dcf40-ce45-42ac-8d58-de4be0c04ab1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/bd9dcf40-ce45-42ac-8d58-de4be0c04ab1/</guid><description>&lt;p>Nagoya Global Friends is an international community in Nagoya whose events gather people from all over the world. In order to visualize the various countries represented, I designed a simple Firebase application. The application allows users to register their home country, which gets stored in a Firestore database. The data is then displayed as a 3D globe with markers for each record.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/65d163cf12a3120013538c56" alt="Article image">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The interface is built using Svelte and the &lt;a href="https://threlte.xyz/">Threlte&lt;/a> library for 3D rendering. Its source code is available on &lt;a href="https://github.com/maximemoreillon/countries-tracker">GitHub&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Habit tracker</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/56e285eb-3b1f-436a-b56a-39f0c69245a1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/56e285eb-3b1f-436a-b56a-39f0c69245a1/</guid><description>&lt;p>Maintaining good habits can sometimes be hard. Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve been looking at the way contributions are displayed on GitHub: a grid with a cell for each day, turning green if contributions have been made on that date.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://img.maximemoreillon.com/images/64571be23581c50013b501a0" alt="Article image">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I realized that it motivated me to write code everyday, just to keep that grid as green as possible. So, I decided to create an app that provides a similar kind of motivation but for habits other than coding daily.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A GUI for ChartMuseum</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/e1d7dd0b-83b9-454e-a6e5-8e72bca46902/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/e1d7dd0b-83b9-454e-a6e5-8e72bca46902/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://chartmuseum.com/">ChartMuseum&lt;/a> is an open-source Helm chart repository server which can be used as a self-hosted alternative to &lt;a href="https://artifacthub.io/">Artifact Hub&lt;/a>. Although it originally consists of only a server-side application to be interacted with via a REST API, its official UI, &lt;a href="https://github.com/chartmuseum/ui">ChartMuseumUI&lt;/a>, can be deployed to interact with ChartMuseum graphically.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unfortunately, ChartMuseumUI seems to be broken and the GitHub repository has been inactive for years now. Thus, I decided to make my own GUI for ChartMuseum.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A simple comparison of Svelte and Vue</title><link>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/f027e7b5-2aef-4ea4-8bc6-c52c50c3eaf1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://articles.maximemoreillon.com/articles/f027e7b5-2aef-4ea4-8bc6-c52c50c3eaf1/</guid><description>&lt;p>Since its introduction in 2019, Svelte has quickly become one of the most loved JavaScript framework overtaking Vue.js in the State of JS ranking 2021 survey. This article presents a simple comparison of Vue.js and Svelte as an attempt to explain why.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="vuejs">Vue.js&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The comparison starts with the Vue.js implementation of a simple counter button. As of version 3 of Vue.js, components can be written in either the Options API of Composition API fashion so both are shown hereunder.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>